<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Royall psalmes or, soliloquies of D. Anthony, King of Portingall. Wherein the sinner confesseth his sinnes, and imploreth the grace of God. / Translated into French by P. Durier ; into English by Baldwin St George, Gent.</title>
            <title>Psalmi confessionales. English</title>
            <author>António, Prior of Crato, 1531-1595.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 67 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75483</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3519</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E2121_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R22834</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871840</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871840</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170576</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75483)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170576)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 242:E2121[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Royall psalmes or, soliloquies of D. Anthony, King of Portingall. Wherein the sinner confesseth his sinnes, and imploreth the grace of God. / Translated into French by P. Durier ; into English by Baldwin St George, Gent.</title>
                  <title>Psalmi confessionales. English</title>
                  <author>António, Prior of Crato, 1531-1595.</author>
                  <author>St. George, Baldwin.</author>
                  <author>Du Ryer, Pierre, d. 1658.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 65, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Humphrey Moseley, and are to be sold at his shop at the Prince's Armes in S. Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title: Royall psalms.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Penance --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Devotional literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170576:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ROYALL PSALMES, OR, SOLILOQUIES OF D. <hi>ANTHONY, KING</hi> OF PORTINGALL. Wherein the Sinner confeſſeth his Sinnes, and imploreth the Grace of GOD.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated into French By <hi>P. DURIER.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Into Engliſh by <hi>Baldwin</hi> St <hi>George,</hi> Gent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Humphrey Moſeley,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the <hi>Prince's Armes</hi> in S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1659.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:170576:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170576:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Tres-Haute et Tres Illuſtre</hi> PRINCESSE Francois de Lorraine, Ducheſſe DE VENDOSME.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>L me ſemble que ces Pſeames, qui ſont ſortis d'une main Royale, ne pouvient r'entrer en de plus il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtres mains que les voſtres, Ils ont eſté Compoſez par un Roy, &amp; Je les preſente à une Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, dont la vertue n'eſt pas moins eſtimable que les ſceptres &amp; les Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronnes. Je ſcaybien que n'ayant pas cet'eſprit de pieté qui eſt ſi neceſſaire
<pb facs="tcp:170576:3"/> pour faire valoir les ouvrages de cette nature, Je n'ay pû auſſy leur donner cette ardeur ſalutaire qui touche les pecheurs, &amp; que leur premier autheur leur a ſi utilement donnee, mais c'eſt Aſſez que l'on ſcache que voſtre Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deur ne les a pas ded'aigne pour croire qu'ils ſeront profitables. Ainſi, Madame, je les ay ſeulement comen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cez, en leur donnant des paroles pour les faire entendre en noſtre Langue &amp; j'eſpere que vous les acheverez par voſtre approbation, Je ne chercheray point icy d'artifice pour obliger vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtre Grandeur de les recevoir favora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blement, Je ſuis aſſuré, Madame, que vous n'y verrez rien qui ne vous plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, puis que vous n'y verrez rien qui ne réjouiſſe les Anges Meſmes. C'eſt un pecheur qui ſe repent de ſes fautes qui implore la miſerecorde de ſon dieu, &amp; qui fait de ſa converſion, la plus grande felicité qu'il puiſſe trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſur la terre. Il ne parle pas de lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage de la cour, parce qu'il ſcait bien que ce n'eſt pas le langage de dieu.
<pb facs="tcp:170576:3"/> Il aime mieux concevoir de bons de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirs, que de prononcer de belles paroles; &amp; pour-veu qu'il puiſſe dire qu'a pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, ill croit eſtre aſſez eloquent, Je m'imagine done,</p>
            <p>Madame, que vouz aimerez le pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheur en ce glorieux eſtat &amp; que vous vous divertirez quelquesfois à luy voir répandre des larmes, dont le repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tir eſt la ſource. C'eſt un divertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, qui n'eſt jamais deſagreable aux ames vertueuſes &amp; ſainctes, &amp; y eſt en cette occaſion qu'on peut legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſouhaiter de voir ſouſpirer ſon pro chain. Jeſuis</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Madame,</salute> 
               <signed> De voſtre Grandeur le tres-humble, tres-obeiſſant, &amp; tres-fidelle Serviteur, DURYER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:170576:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170576:4"/>
            <head>To the truly HONORABLE, Noble, and moſt vertuous Lady, The Lady <hi>ANNE INGOLDSBY.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y apprehenſive quil drew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in its baſhfull Inke, at the preſumption to fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tispiece ſo mean a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, as a Tranſlation, with an Inſcription to a Perſon of ſo much Honour, ſo much worth, ſo thronged an Inventory, and ſo compleat a <hi>Synopſis,</hi> of all Perfections. But embold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, first, by the Precedent of the French Tranſlator; ſecondly, encouraged by the
<pb facs="tcp:170576:5"/> Piety of the Subject; moved thirdly, by the Nobleneſſe of the Author: It hath diſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ſome obliged drops towards this Dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to your Ladyſhip of a French treatiſe, done into the Engliſh dialect, to an unparallel'd Miſtriſs in both, of a Pious ſubject to a pious Patroneſſe, of a No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Author to a Noble Lady. Madam, you ſhall here behold a Royal Convert: The Angells rejoyce at the Converſion of a ſinner; and, as your vertues intitle you to their Fellowſhip, and ſomething above mortall in your beauty to their reſemblance, you muſt neceſſarily partake of their Joy, and fill up the quire of that Coeleſtiall Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erarchy with your Allelujah's. And ſeeing nothing but a little Clay (which although in reference to your Ladyſhip's amiable Symmetry, is ſtamped with a preparative Angelicall Impreſſe) detaineth you from the preſent enjoyment of their bleſſed So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety; you cannot nevertheleſſe but be alike moved with them, and will (I hope) afford the Gracious Influence of your Protecting beames to the unworthy Interpreter of theſe welcome Tydings, and crown him
<pb facs="tcp:170576:5"/> (which is the higheſt ayme his ambition levells at) with a Crown, ſtudded and enammell'd with your ſmiles. As this Conſideration ſeemed to extenuate my boldneſſe; So, the Univerſall engaging ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of your dispoſition, the obliging Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digallity of your favours to me in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, and the deep ſenſe of gratitude to your noble family and relations, VVarran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Inſcription, and Commands the Subſcription of</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Madam,</salute> 
               <signed>Your Ladiſhip's moſt humble and vowed Servant. B. St. <hi>George.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="soliloquies">
            <pb facs="tcp:170576:6"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170576:6"/>
            <head>
               <hi>ROYALL</hi> PSALMES: OR, SOLILOQUIES OF D. <hi>ANTHONY, KING</hi> OF <hi>PORT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>GALL.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="soliloquy">
               <head>Wherein the Sinner confeſſeth his Sinnes, and imploreth the Grace of GOD.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hence ſhall I exhale tears enough to pay a deluge for the ſtrayings and diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of my ſoul? When I throw my Conſiderations on the paſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trod paths of my life, and caſt a ſpecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170576:7"/> optick on the paſſages of my youth, horror and ſadneſſe arreſts my ſurvey. This reflection on my ſelfe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verberates to my ſoul nothing but trembling, nothing but condemnation, nothing but diſpaire, nothing but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion. I know what I have bin, I have known what I ought to have bin, I know not now what I am. I appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend what I ſhall bee: And the leſſe my ſorrow is for offending God, the more the apprehenſions of it, is enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged.</p>
               <p>Why cannot I repent more, that I may fear leſſe? Alas! I have bin long under thy ſcourge (O Lord) and the heavineſſe of thy hand makes me feel the weight of my tranſgreſſions; yet cannot I fix a repentant kiſſe to that Rod. Long haſt thou lured me, yet I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine ſtill unreclaimed; long haſt thou rais'd and plai'd thy Batteries to force a paſſage to my heart; yet I, ſo much my owne enemy, deny an amicable Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veiw to one who brings and offers life. A thouſand evills caſt up their trenches
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170576:7"/> round about me, death threateneth me in the van, flank, and reare; and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I am ſtorm'd with all ſorts of calamities and afflictions, yet my ſoul hath not one hoſtage-teare to ranſome my ſalvation. Theſe ills have not only ataqued mine age; my life and ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings comenced together, from my youth I am a man of ſorrow: In fine, I may on the counters of my dyſaſters, caſt up the ſingle moments of my life; and now I ſuffer, becauſe ſuffering taught me not repentance for my faults. O the admirable prudence of the heavenly and great Phyſitian! O the immenſe goodneſs of the King of kings the Soveraign of heaven and earth! O the bountifull openneſſe of that hand that ſtroweth about its favours! O my God, thou underbladders't me with greifs, that I may not ſink in pleaſures, that I may learne to rejoyce, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out making my Joyes criminall, thou delegates ſorrows finite, to attone for ſorrowes Infinite; thou diſmantles my body of comforts, to cloathe my ſoul
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170576:8"/> with ſalvation. The wounds that thou inflicts, are but to open an eaſier expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to my cure; and thou endanger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt not my preſent life, but as a preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vative to a life more happy, more glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, more triumphant. But alas! what is neceſſary for me, falls ſo little under my cognizance, that I check at the phyſick of thy mercifull preſcripts, I dread thoſe afflictions, whoſe rigorous violence ought to inſtruct, and ought to be received as effects rather of mercy then of choler: ſo that I fail in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhing the counter-poyſons thou tendereſt: and how ſhall I diſtinguiſh them, being not to be cured but by af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction? yet I deſire to be freed from an affliction ſo wholſome. To conclude, can there bud any hopes of a cure but from griefs? Seeing ſickneſſe and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes are the fruits of pleaſure, let me ſuffer them, (O Lord my God) but to the end that my ſorrows may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted into Ioyes, and I rejoyce with thee; teach me how my ſufferings may meet with thy divine pleaſure and my owne ſalvation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="soliloquy">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:170576:8"/>
               <head>PSALM II.</head>
               <p>TIme with a ſwift current tides away yeares and dayes, yet my unhappineſſe ſtill fixeth my condition; I am ſtill a ſinner, ſtill call downe the viall of my God's Indignation. Having been conſtantly wracked on the wheel of ſo many afflictions, ſo many miſeries; they have not forced from me ſo much as one good thought, one ſenſible de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation of my ſins, the ſole Axle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree whereon my misfortunes turne. I regard not how I lend an advantage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous foot to each dayes ſinfull trips, but have not regard to recover my foyls; I ſtill patch up my old iniquities with new offences, and ſtep from petty treſpaſſes to capital; how ſhall I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine the ſtroak of my laſt hour? how ſhall I fly? where ſhall I conceal my guilty head, when Judgment ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons to an appearance, and I am cited to bring in my audit for my manifold receipts? at what a bluſh will my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>excuſable ſloath &amp; negligence, tongue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tied
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170576:9"/> ſtand, when I ſhall behold the awe of thy enthroned Majeſty, and muſt paſſe a ſtrict ſcrutiny for the leaſt pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cadilloes in my behaviour and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernments? I wil reply then, my God, I am over-charged, O let thy mercy be an advocate in my cauſe: who am I and where ſhall I find eloquence to make my tongue fertill with a rejoynder to thy Juſtice? but what ſhall I do if thou urge a plea? I muſt with a trembling baſhfullneſſe wrap my face in confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and acknowledge I have not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved the ſtock wherewith I was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted, I muſt confeſſe I have misdiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burſed it in vanities, and that it hath ſerved as an exchequer to maintaine my luſts, and that I have laviſhed it in living ſinfully. Alas? did I ſay [in li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving]? it is not an expreſſion fit to cloath that condition; I ſhould rather ſay in dying. I imagin'd I lived in the dayes of my voluptuouſneſſe, but now a thorough-conviction lyes upon my ſoul I was dead, becauſe I lived without Thee, the only true life. How ſhould I
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170576:9"/> live when my memory affords not one inſtance that I have lived with thee: In fine, (O my God) ſince the life of a ſinner is death; I may truly conclude, my death anticipated my life; as yet I am not acquainted with life, but ſtil re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main in an empty channel cut off from my God the head and fountaine of life. My corrupt inclinations ſtill. impreg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated my tender age with occaſions of offending thee, I was ſcarce enfranchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from the womb, when I ſell into the bondage of ſin: At my nativity, my cheeks were bedewed with teares for ſins I was conceived in and knew not. And I had ſcarce dryed up the teares for the ſins of another, but I began to commit ſins my ſelf which I did know, yet have not lent them one teare. I have delighted my ſelfe in the ſins of my infancy, and with my impurities prophan'd the innocency of that age which nature intended the Sanctuary and ſacred treaſury of all the purity of this life. I have breathed nothing but concupiſcence, I have been the ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full triumph of my baſe and ſinfull af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170576:10"/> and a web ſo thick hath ſpread it ſelfe over the eye of my underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, that I could not diſcern between light and darkneſſe, between the ſmooth calmeneſſe of the mind, and the tempeſtuous Billows of ſenſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. In an age ſo ignorant and ſo little ſtudious of good, I have given a quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er care to the world then to heaven, I have bin driven down the ſwift torrent of a deceitfull voluptuous ſtream; and, as if I had been carried away more with the love of torments then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, I have acted here on Earth whatſoever might further my inevita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble precipice into hell. From a corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted infancy I have proceeded to a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauched puberty; my ſins have ſhooted up with my yeares and have grown whilſt I grew. My vaine and vitious loves, put on me the ſhape of a mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man or barbarian; and at the ſame time I was philtred and enchanted, by their luſhious witchcrafts. I became mine own enemy, and willingly ran into the fatall embraces of my own ruine. The dayes of my puberty were graduates
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170576:10"/> in the ſchooles of ſinne. Through the courſe of ſinning I paſſed to the degree of my Youth, which has left behind it no other tracts but the ſoyls and ſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyings of vice; every moment that adds to my age adds to my ſins. I have bin young, I have attain'd the viril conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtency of a man, and diſſeiſing vice hath alwayes held the ſigniory of my Soul which owed allegiance unto vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue. Age hath ſwan-plum'd my el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der head, yet it ſo little maturates my judgment, that I tread not in the paths of thy heavenly directions; and as if I were a child, at a double Jubilee of yeares, old and craſie as I am, yet do I the actions of a Child. What time hath bin ſo unprivy to my faults that it may encourage the leaſt plea of Innocency? Alas! my God if thou ſhould'ſt gratifie me, to expect untill I pick'd out one moment of Innocency in my whole life, to move in arreſt of Judgement; what advantage could I take of that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, ſince my life affords not one mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute but loaden with a ſin? Thou art Juſt (my God,) thy Judgements are
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170576:11"/> Juſtice it ſelfe; thy deciſions match the merits of the cauſe. When I ſeek for appeaſing inducements, I find in me nothing but provoking motives. All my accounts carry the juſtice of a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited fear, And I cannot reckon them without ſumming up my tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. I have bin alwayes active in ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, I have conſtantly footed the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the wicked, their inſtructions have been alwayes my charming mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick. I have wallowed in vices like a ſwine in the mire, whoſe repaſt is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure and filth; nor have I fancied my ſelfe, in other than in things vaine, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractious, and blaſphemous; whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever was wholeſome became nauſeous; and that only had the guſt to tickle my wanton palate which was mortiferous, my Boſome-councell were the wicked. I had no enjoyment but in the ſociety of the reprobate; my ambition was to aim at the wretched grandure of an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent ſinner. I was dextrous in excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, ſlow in accuſing my ſelfe. To ſteel; and harden my heart, was the butt of my bended endeavours; and the not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acknowledging
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170576:11"/> my ſelfe a ſinner, the more aggravation it heaped on my ſins, the leſſe minorations is left my excuſes, I was negligent in procuring Balſome for my wounded ſoul, ſleighted all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipe's, and grew enraged againſt thoſe beyond the limits of all reaſon and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect vvho forced a ſeaſonable Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy. I have knit my fiſts at the inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or, and opened my armes to the flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer; my eares have not admitted-in thy peace-propounding-trumpets, but given audience to thoſe that came without thy orders. In fine, (my God,) the vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the world hath been the whole courſe of my ſtudies. All my diſcourſes were lies, in the addreſſes of all my af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, I have courted darkneſſe before light. See here the landskip of my acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſee the card of my whole life! Where is there any thing to be found but provocatives of thy juſt indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? So that I will anſwer thy interro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatories with nothing but humble con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions; and ſince thou haſt taught me, ſelfe-accuſation proves the moſt accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table excuſe, I will ſue out my Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:170576:12"/> with the bare acknowledgment of my crimes; raſe out from thy memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the diſorders of my youth, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite me not at the Barre of thy Juſtice. It is impoſſible for man to be juſtified before thee: but, if I muſt paſſe thorough thy judgments, turne me over (O God) to the Bench of thy Mercy, and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber I am the workmanſhip of thy own hands, although a ſinner. If my ſins provoke, let thy mercy appeaſe; let its interceſſion merit the repentance of him that adores thee; let it bound thy juſtly-incenſed wrath; In fine, let it ſnatch me out of the fiery embraces of hell, to the end my ſoul may eccho forth thy praiſes, and trump, through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all the corners of the earth, the effects of thy clemency.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="soliloquy">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:170576:12"/>
               <head>PSALM III.</head>
               <p>WHat an aggravated unhappi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is it, to have incenſed the author of happineſs, to have offended the purchaſer of Salvation, and to have deſpiſed ſo ſuperciliouſly his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts? I have willingly quitted the pathes of felicity, and like a ſtray ſheep wandred and ſtraggled within the ſhot and command of all occaſions, that might gape after and deſign my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction; I have roved every where, and every where been aſſayled by troops of ſorrows, griefs, and misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes. I have been wildred in the Meanders of perdition and iniquity. I have left no place unbeaten, that I might ſpring to my ſelf repoſe and conſolation; but I retriv'd them not, becauſe I minded not Thee, my God. Without enquiring after the territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of peace, I have travelled through a Barren land, the demeanſns of death and ſinne, where horror and pain en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camp, and where the Soul lyes ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to the Marſhalſey of everlaſting
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170576:13"/> torments. Whilſt I glittered in pomp and dignity, I was daſl'd with their coruſcancy; and as if I had been Nabucadonoſer'd into a beaſt, Woods and Caves were my ſhelters. Whilſt I was mired in pleaſures, I was plung'd in troubles, my couche was prepar'd on a precipice; at the ſame inſtant both ſleep and ruine crept upon me; ſuch a miſt interpoſed the beames of my rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that I expected anchorage in the midſt of ſo many ſtormes, and ſo many perils. What courſe ſhall I ſteere, in what creek ſhall I ſecure my ſelfe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing beaten on a lee-ſhore, amidſt the ſhelves and ſhoales of encompaſſing dangers? The hopes that convoyed my youth are diſperſed and vaniſhed, and I am become like to one ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracked, who having loſt his veſſell ſends a watery eye after his floating treaſures: ſcourged hither and thither by the tyrannous winds and no leſs im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perious waves, I am farre from har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors, can kenne no land that gives hopes of eſcape, I let my ſelf be dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven on the rocks where I muſt moſt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170576:13"/> miſerably periſh. The Enimy hath planted his Ambuſcadoes and I never miſtruſted, I have walked without fear or ſuſpition over the pit-falls he hath covered for me; and, as if I were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to my owne perdition, I have clapp'd an extinguiſher on the light that ſhould guide to their diſcovery. I have ſoothed my ſelf in my ſinnes, nor could I faſten in my Imagination the leaſt opinion of homage due from my youth to the Signiorie of death. Thus my Soul being over-reached by the vanity of that falſe poſition, gave entertainment to all extravagant ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petites. I held forth a willing arme to uſhering ſenſuality, and was carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed whereſoever her policy and ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny led me. Why, ſaid I, (diſputing with my ſelf) ſhould I dream of death? why ſhould I fixe my thoughts on the end before the middle hath taken up my conſiderations; life enough is left unſpunne to meditate a recollection, a ſuddain converſion waites on my will at all ſeaſons. Thus have I grown old in my impieties, thus are my ill
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170576:14"/> cuſtomes become habituall, and thus as a Gally-ſlave to ſinne, chain'd to its oare, I muſt obey. I am like unto a lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natique that hates both life and body, and armes his fury againſt the one and the other, untill his totally ſopited and beſotted reaſon leaves to command his actions. But alaſs, the bent of my hate is of a nature more ſtrange, more pernitious! The lunatick faſtens on his body, bends but his fiſt and blows a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt clay: but my obdurateneſſe in ſinne makes me faſten on my Soul, and conclude its wounds in murther. Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving thus climbed by degrees to the top of Iniquity, day after day I irri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate my God, and my obſtinacy calls upon the juſtice of his fury and my perdition. I have been often forced to ſmoother the inveterate and wicked flames that prey upon me. But it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to ſecure my heart from them; their fewell is in mee, they are lodg'd in my bones. O my God, ſpread thy gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious wings over me! I am not able to quench this deſtroying fire, but with the ſaving fire of thy divine love. I
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170576:14"/> have not ſtrength enough to caſt off the yoke of ſinne: thy aſſiſtance muſt work my diſ-ingagement, and thy ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cors muſt prove the reſerves to my weaker forces. My deſerts (I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe) dare not move for theſe favours; but, ſince thy goodneſſe cauſeth the ſunne to comfort the good and bad with the radiancy of an equall Influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; and that thou layeſt thy obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions on the unworthy, and on thoſe that beg them not at thy hands; I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not conceive thou wilt be ſo thrifty of thy ſpirituall riches towards one that begs with the vehemency of ſo Intent an ardour, and with the deep ſenſe of ſo much ſorrow for his offences. Move thy compaſſion towards me, give eare to the humble ſute of a poor wretch, thou that art rich in mercies thou that glorieſt in the facility of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning, thou that waſheſt away the evill habits of the will, thou that hearkens to the complaints of the cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, thou that breakeſt the Netts we pitch for our ſelves, thou that buyeſt our liberty when we ſell our ſelves to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170576:15"/> ſlavery, and imploy the falſe liberty (men think they injoy without thee) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee: ſtretch forth thy hands that the worke of thy hands may not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, that I may not fall into the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomleſſe pitt that affords not one drop of watter to quench the everlaſting flames that tortures ſinners: deliver me from the Jawes of the roaring Lyon who ſearcheth me for his prey, and vvill not leave off his bloodthirſting ſcent: thou, vvho art my Protector, and in vvhoſe mercy all my hopes caſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor, let the effects of thy mercies an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the hopes of them; becauſe I have hoped in thee my God, I ſhall not be confounded; and having in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion taſted the returnes of my pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, I vvill beare a part to thy glory vvith the heavenly Quires of Angells and bleſſed Spirits.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="soliloquy">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:170576:15"/>
               <head>PSALM IV.</head>
               <p>MY nightly couch hath been cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd about with melancholy; feare and terrour have given their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>welcome attendance to my fancy, my conſcience makes mortal and re-itera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thruſts, nor am I dexterous enough to ward its paſſes; and the leaſt wound I receive, is from the tuck of an Enimy. I cannot allay my diſquieting thoughts; hovering Illuſions interrupt my ſleeps, inſtead of affording its naturall repoſe, it miniſters to my inquietude. It is an impoſſibility, ſleep ſhould attaque my eye-lids; if a wearineſſe ſtroak my tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples with the hopes of a ſlumber, a reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſſe in me fruſtrates its blanditions. I feele a late, what devouring fire creeps through my entrailes which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivs recruits from my watchings. The food diſreliſheth that reliſhed before. I mingle teares with my Beverage, my forehead is bound about with confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſhame ſpreds it ſelfe over my face. When I ruminate on my offences to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards my God, and in how many
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170576:16"/> ſundry wayes I have abuſed my owne abilityes and his favours. The ſtudy of vanity hath Ingroſs'd the ſum of my dayes, I grow pale with cares oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to my good, permitting my ſelfe to be carried away with the extravagan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of my conceipts and the Injuſtice of my deſires: my loſſe is become Irrepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, I have let ſlip the time deſtin'd for the working forth of my ſalvation, I fed my Imagination with dreames, my eyes ſeem'd to entertaine nothing but realities, and they proved meere deluſions. In fine, I have deceived my ſelf; my vanities and ravings have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired my ruine, my aymes reached heaven, and the depth of Hell received me; and ſince my veterane ſins teeme new offences, and one abyſſe draweth another Abyſſe, my ſoul enervated by vice is become feeble, and I am now as rottenneſs in the Noſthrills of men. My wiſhes catch at impoſſibilities, and the imaginary poſſeſſion of them renders me not unlike to one, who dreaming golden dreames, at his awaking is ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with a regretfull corroſive for his
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170576:16"/> vaniſhed treaſure. I am but a worme, (my God) yet ſuch a ſtranger to my ſelfe I have had an aſpiring boldneſſe rearedme over the tops of others heads; all my diſcourſes have beene tipped with faſtuous affectation, I conceived the elixar of wiſdome to conſiſt in that pride. I became intolerable to thoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled me, a fantaſtique groundleſſe choler hath often hurried me on to be injurious. This cruell paſſion was ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, my ſoul itſelfe nurſed it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the leaſt incouragement of a provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation: ſo long as it raigned in me, not only my ſelfe, ſervants, and relations, but I my ſelf participated the fury of its tyranny. And, without conſideration how God upraided me not with the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſity of his favors, I hit my freinds in the teeth with ſcarce obliging civilities. I have murmured under the preſſure of my misfortunes, I have placed my hopes in man, and waved my confidence in God. I entertained truth with deafneſs, wholſome documents with offence, the inſtructor with anger, the pilots of ſalvation with diſlike; my genius hath
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170576:17"/> bin abuſive. I have courted vengeance for the leaſt affront or punctillio, and anticipated the prerogative of God, whoſe prerogative it is to revenge. I have bin diſreſpectfull to the Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainers of a good cauſe. Retorts, although ſeaſoned with ſweetneſſe and humility, moved my choler: what was good in the good ſquared not with my humor, Brawls and contentions made up my divertiſements, I was a skilfull pioneer in undermining the friendſhip of Bretheren, and in manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſcord and hatred amongſt them to the beſt advantage: good inſtructions have touched my theory, but were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver welcomed by my practiſe; they have knockt at my eares, but were not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted into my heart. I have carreſſed evill counſellors, whoſe endeavors were to pleaſe, they have filled a choiſe place in my ſavour. But I fancied not a tell-troth, nor thoſe that with a whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome freedome both hinted at my im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections and perſued them with a pious correction. I have not ſtretched forth my hand to thoſe in diſtreſſe, and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170576:17"/> who ſnatched at my needful aſſiſtance. I have not ſhared my morſells with the poor, whom death had beleagured with famine and neceſſity. I have tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned mine eyes from the begger and the ſick, leſt a ſenſible compaſſion ſhould triumph over my avarice and engage an Almes. I have had no care to diſcharge my debts, nor to reſtore the depoſitums to thoſe who confided in me; with the greater facility. To anſwer my unlimitted deſires, I have bankrup't my neighbor by borrowing what I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver reſtored: I groped after wealth, but as an eaſier expedient to ſin. I have ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared rich upon a vaine and ſinfull account, but alwaies poor upon a cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable one. I wanted nothing to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain my concupiſcence, I wanted every thing to treat piety. I have baniſhed moderation from my trencher, &amp; with horrid exceſſes overcharged nature that is ſatisfied with a little, and is the very ſchoolemiſtris of temperance. I have paied a ſtrange Idolatry to my Belly, I have built my glory upon an earthly foundation, which could threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170576:18"/> nothing but diſtruction. The moſt exquiſite rarities have been ſearched for to furniſh out my table, I have fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gned inconveniencies to excuſe my ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities; neceſſity hath been often urged as a pretext for my gluttony: my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placency hath bin with addultreſſes, I have loved the converſation of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continent. My impurities have ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to ſuch a pitch that I have not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence to expreſſe what I have had confidence to commit. I have bound out my eares and tongue apprentices to vanity; with a favorable attention I have ſucked in flatteries; and when in my opinion my prayſes came ſhort, I have made them up with them of my owne mintage. When an occaſion of applauſe has bin offered, I have bin tic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kled with applauding my ſelfe and with the applauſe of others. In terreſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all delicacies I have forfeited the cates of heaven; if at any time the apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive horror of death and Judgment dreweth me ſorth of that pitt which the entregues of worldly pleaſures hath ſunck for us, at the ſame inſtant
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170576:18"/> I ſlip back againe, I am like to a dog that returnes to his vomit. I am dead as to good workes, I ſtill live in ſinns, and although a neere borderer on the frontiers of death, nevertheleſſe undiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maied with the terrour and dreadfull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of its approaches, I run upon it, But (O my God) let thy great compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion antevert that great day, that fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full day, that day of teares and groanes; prepare me by death to the commence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of life, that I may fill the whole creation with encomiums of thy mercy. Behold (O Lord,) behold the poſture of my ſoule, behold the ſtreights my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence hath brought it in, behold the ſtripes of that Fury; preſerve me from the power of an enemy that will prove inconquerable, unleſſe thy aux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iliary forces intervene. Knock off the ſhackles &amp; bolts of death, (O my God) that I may chaine my ſelfe to thee, who alone art the true life; and that have<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing caſt away the care of all things, I may follow thee, who art more conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable then all things. Lord my God, God of mercy and ſalvation, whiſper to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170576:19"/> my ſoul, I am thy ſafeguard, thy pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers are accepted, let it be done unto thee according to thy petition; let ſuch a voice (my God) draw my attention, that following thee I may encounter thee, encountring thee I may never de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from thee untill thou returns me whole. For where ſhall I find phyſick for my greifs, if I repair not to thee my God; and who can prove a more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert phyſitian for my infirmities than he who hath ſtoop'd from heaven for the reparation of mankin'd, and to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply remedies to his maladies? who can better beſtow life than he, in whoſe hands is both life and death? who can be a better pledge for my ſalvation amongſt the gulphs and precipices of this world, than my God and my Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our? Save me then, enlighten me then, thou art both the author of ſalvation and life, to thoſe repoſe their truſt in thee. And as thy power (my God) had no alpha, let thy glory have no omega; that we may magnifie thee, that we may adore thee, that we may erect im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal trophics to thy honour and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:170576:19"/> everlaſting thanks to thee, who art the eternall fountaine of mercyes. I have bin eſtranged from thee, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though my eſtrangeneſſe was an act of my owne will, thou haſt not failed to anſwer the beginning of my invocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons with a timely aſſiſtance: The quick applications of thy remedies have even prevented my complaints, the very will to be cured perfects the cure, and to will life is a motive ſufficient to thy goodneſſe that we receive it; the extent of thy bounty is ſo large, thy graces commonly anticipate the prayers of a repenting ſinner. I will confeſs, my God, and that will be a ſatisfactory allay to thy indignation, how that I am conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous of my Iniquities, how that I am ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with my evill doings, and do wil a preſent cure. Yea, my God, it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary I know them, that the horrour I have may be implanted in my bones, and that my ſoul may be affrighted at the terrible Image my memory copieth forth. I diſcover to thy Divine Majeſty my imperfections and my ſins, to the end thy Mercy may raſe and pumice
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170576:20"/> them forth, and thou maieſt enlighten the darke capacity of my ſoule that misleads me to a rebellion againſt thee. As thou wilt not the Iniquity, ſo thou deſires not the death of a ſinner, but that he be converted and live: the dead ſhall not praiſe thee (my God) none but thee living, none but we ſhall be thy Panegyriks, Quireſters, and Trump, through all ages, the fullneſſe of thy mercies and the tenor of thy bounties.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="soliloquy">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:170576:20"/>
               <head>PSALM, V.</head>
               <p>BEfore thee (my God) have I ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med up my miſeries, not for thy information, not to make known the Condition wherein I ſtand, nor the paths I trace in the world; becauſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready they are fallen under thy eternall preſcience, and from eternity thou haſt numbered my foot-ſteps. Thou pierceſt through the obſcurity of darkneſs, thou diſcloſeſt all cloſſets, there is nothing can withdraw it ſelf from thy ſight, to thee are all things preſent, thou dive'ſt into the Cabinet-counſells of our hearts, our moſt ſecret thoughts to thee are patent. I will therefore lay open my miſeries that thou maiſt uncover thy mercy, and ſpread over me thy protecting wing: I will reveale my ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets that thou mayeſt conceale them, that thou mayeſt be ſatisfied with the humility and brokenneſſe of my heart, that by a ſacrifice ſo propitiatory, I may invite a plenary expiation of my offences. I have hitherto caſt up an au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit of things horrible, yet the reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:170576:21"/> falls ſhort of what I have commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. My conſcience allarums me with continuall aſſaults, continually repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents the horrid Ideas of my treſpaſſes, and ingenders in my ſoul a worm that bites and corrodes without intermiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but why may not the knawing cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſive of this worm conſume all impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities, and in conſuming them conſume it ſelfe? My God, let it not ſo feed that it may live eternally, let it feed that it may dye, and that, by feeding, by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees it may leave to feed. But alas! how deplorable is my caſe. I believed the latitude of my confeſſion had cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſcribed my ſins, but I muſt confeſſe it admits of larger bounds, my memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſtill affords freſh inſtances of a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved fear from thy Juſtice; and as it ſwells with the whole iniquity of my life, it is no ſooner delivered of one particular, but it groweth big with particulars more heinous, more crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall. Were the ſand of the ſea multipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into figures it were an arithmetick too skant to caſt up my tranſgreſſions. Were my tongue centupled it were ſtill
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:170576:21"/> impoſſible to count one of a million: ſo that my greif is the more intenſe by reaſon all my impurities come not within the compaſſe of my memory, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the wedgery of new offences drive and peg out the old ones. But (my God) thoſe I will not wrap up in ſilence my remembrance hath bundled up, I will remove my affection from them, that I may the more firmly ſettle it on Thee, that thou weighing the humility of my ſoul and an eye floating in teares, thy ſeverity may be abated, and thy ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſweetneſſe encouraged. Thou who art the reall ſweetneſſe, the ſweetneſſe that entraps not, the bleſſed ſweetneſſe, the ſweetneſſe moſt aſſured and perma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent. I have entertained kindneſſe with envy and malice, charity with diſre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect. Kings Princes and the miniſters of the Goſpel have been under the laſh of my tongue, with outragious mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murings I have ſcandalized them; en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comiums of the good received reproof, the actions of the wicked approbation; if at any time the juſt were juſtly applauded, at the ſame time my endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170576:22"/> were to ſully their reputations with impoſtures. I have ſifted out their moſt hidden failings. I have bin ſo cenſoriouſly rigid towards them, into grand crimes have I aggravated their petty treſpaſſes: on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, if the wicked received their due ſalary of a juſt infamy, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently fell into diſreſpute and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credit with the world, I have imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly backed them, I have extolled their imaginary vertues, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd them before the juſt; and perhaps have proved the ultimate cauſe to their perdition. I have combined with the thiefe in purloyning my neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor's goods; and that nothing may be wanting to compleate my iniquity, I have fathered the ſcandall on the ſon of my mother; my friends and relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons could not ſecure themſelves from my frauds, nor ſhelter themſelves from my calumnies. What inundations of miſeries and misfortunes was poſſible to breake in upon mortalls, my mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious wiſhes poured on my neighbor's head. In his death have I often laied the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170576:22"/> foundation of my hopes. I have not ſpred a protecting wing over the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent; and as if the dyſaſters of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate were a pleaſing harmony to me, with inhumane reproaches I have tun'd their afflictions, to the higheſt key.</p>
               <p>The greateſt part in the world hath ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered in the raſhneſs of my judgment, I have condemned for ſins things with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the evidence of the leaſt ſuſpition, I have perceived the moate in my bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers eye without ſeeing the beame in my owne, I have bin lulled in ſloath and Idleneſſe, ſhunn'd honeſt labors and vertuous exerciſes, I have drowned my time in a voluntary lethargie. My God, my thoughts were never buſied about thankefull returnes for thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours; nor hath thy lawes and thy power taken up my meditations. Thou knoweſt (O God) how ſleep hath often quitted its nightly quarters on my eylids, and my minde that entertain'd the thought of every thing elſe, was only unhoſpitable to the thought of thee. It hath flown every where, but never perched on thee. I have prepared
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:170576:23"/> for bed, I have ſetled my ſelfe to ſleep, I have awaked without dreaming of thee. I have been alwaies without thee becauſe I dwelt ſo much with my ſelf; nor perſued I any thing but dark paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions which conſtantly widned the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance from thee. If at any time ejacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latory thoughts ſoared towards thee and pried into the wonders thou haſt perpetrated for mankind, before they vvere yet flegg I ſmoothered them. I have permitted my ſelfe to be philtred by the ſvveet poyſon of the vvorld's vanity The endeavours I uſe to teach my ſpeculations thy grandeurs, are not unlike the endeavours uſed tovvard that of ſleep, vvhich vvhen the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanting flattery of it once overcomes, there enſueth none more ſound. I have voted often the ſettlement of my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, but ſtill adjourn'd it till the morrovv; the hopes to amend one day hath cutt off all hopes of amendment. I have placed my felicity on a tottering and deceitfull baſis, I leaned on a reed, a broken ſtaffe, vvhen I thought my
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170576:23"/> footing moſt ſure, I miſerably dropped into the fire; and nothing but my fall could convince me of the ſeebleneſſe of my ſupport. My ambition hath ſnatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at unlavvfull honors, I burnt vvith an imoderate deſire of hoarding up ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and ſqueezing profit out of every thing. Theſe uncurb'd luſts have bogued me in ſinfull plunges and troubles. I have ſhaken hands vvith all the vvick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, vvith all the unrighteous, and all thoſe vvhoſe lives vvere irregular and diſorderly. I have diſhonoured friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, that ſacred tye, that ought to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leige to none but the vertuous: yes (my God) I have diſgraced it vvith concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcences, and have prophaned its ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctity vvith the impurity of my affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, I have fancied my ſelfe in paſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes vvherein lodg'd the cauſe of my perdition, and the fuell to that fire vvhich conſumed me; and inſtead of blocking up the paſſages to obſtruct the inroades of death, I have opened him freſh avenues. All my members have been ſo many portalls to receive him
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:170576:24"/> into my ſoul. VVhen I have ben ſullied vvith new offences, I have not bin clen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from my old iniquities: on the contrary they have rather bin the ſeeds of ſo many crimes which eſtranged me from thy face. That is the reaſon I have been deprived of the conſolation, thy preſence affords, and that I wander like a deſparado, a ſtranger to his own pathes. But alas! what will betide me if I depart from thee? who will throw his eyes on me if thou avert thine, and as a reprobate deny me the favour of thy aſpect? No doubt I ſhall prove odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to men, both a ſubject of ſcorne and deriſion, vvhen they ſhall demand of me, Where is thy God? why hath he e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſed his face from thee? What ſhall I do when outlawed from thy Protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? whither ſhal I go hemmed in on all ſides and deſerted of thee? With teares and ſobbes will I ſearch thee out, I will implore thy mercie, I will beſeech thee not to abandon me, and that thy juſt indignation may not move thee to draw off thy lookes from the guard of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:170576:24"/> thy ſervant; becauſe my enemies per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue me, as if I fled before them, they perſue me (My God) to inſlave me and to carrouſe my blood. It behoofs me therefore to take covert under thee, to flye to thy Protection from whom I have ſo long fled. Thou art my ſtrength (O God) my refuge, my aſſurance. It is thy power alone can countenance me, thy conſolation which can cheere me in the day of my miſeries and affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions. As there is no God but thee, there is no Saviour but thee, Thou my God to whom my miſeries and infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities are patent, before whom Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie is unvailed, forget both my old and my new offences; let thy mercies divert the purſuites of my enemies; file off the bolts I have ſo cruelly been ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ckled with: there is none my God can do it but thee, who crowneth with ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation thoſe that put their truſt in thee, and renders the poore and weake tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant over the proud; and the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſhade not the divine radiancy of thy lookes from me. Diſdaine me not
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:170576:25"/> (O God) be unto me a ſalvation and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance, a redeemer. I am poore and miſerable, thou art accuſtomed to glad the poore and the miſerable with the ſplendor of thy rayes. If thy juſtice hunt to unkennell me, let thy mercy earth me; defend me through thy good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe that makes thee patient and me penitent. Thou art meek, thou art pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, thy mercy overpoiſeth thy wrath, there is nothing more proper to thee, than to compaſſionate the miſerable, to pardon ſinners: the whole world hath taſted of thy loving kindneſſe becauſe thou art omnipotent, thou connives at the tranſgreſſions of mortalls that thou maieſt be pleaſed with their repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, thou forgives becauſe thou loves the world becauſe it is the architecture of thy owne hands. Dart thy ſaving glances on me, that I may turne to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thee, diſingage my afflicted ſoul from the deſperate extremities it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to, that my lips may overflow with thy praiſes, and that I may break forth and ſay, Bleſſed be the Lord, who
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:170576:25"/> hath not permitted me to fall into the hands of my enemies: they had deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me, had not thy timely ſuccour pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented; my ſoul was like to a bird en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangled in the ſnares of the fowler. The nets are broken, and I am delivered.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="soliloquy">
               <pb facs="tcp:170576:26"/>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:170576:26"/>
               <head>PSALM VI.</head>
               <p>WHat ſhall I do, a miſerable and unfortunate object? The mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, ſinne, ſpawn of the bottomleſſe pit, hath ſtained his jawes with the ſlaughter of my ſoul. I have bin led a ſad ſpectacle of my enemie's triumph. My God! he hath ſtript me of all thoſe habiliments, wherewith thou didſt cloath me; I am now abaſhed to lay open my nakedneſſe before thee, I iſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of thy hands, accompliſhed with all the graces and riches might furniſh out a compleat happineſs; and without ſeriouſly weighing the ſle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derneſs of my guard to ſecure them, I have picquered with all occaſions, that might diſmount me, and caſt me into perdition. The Blazon of my ſoul is char-cole-ſable, it hath forfeited the livery colour of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency, and hath bartered for poiſon, celeſtiall viands. That I might habit my ſelfe in the mode of a ſinner, I have caſt off thy pretious equipage and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coutrements.
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:170576:27"/> I have bin to my ſelfe both a defacement and a deſtruction; me-thinks I am moulded into the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute portraiture of the firſt mans dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience. In fine, (my God) ſin hath ſo miſerably metamorphoſed my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, thou wilt ſcarce diſcern in me the ſtamp of thy creating impreſſion: Is it not juſtice then, like a rotten ſheep, to exclude me the flock? If an awfull trembling creep through the heavens at thy ſight, what confidence can lead me into thy preſence, who am nothing but impurity? If from ſinfulneſſe I am lapſed to brutiſhneſs, what impudence can brazen me, to diſcover my face a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Elect? I will nevertheleſſe returne to thee, although feare and ſhame ſtruggle within me; I will lay hold on that fatherly bounty where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with thou embraces all men, as a guide to conduct me into thy boſome, as the affection of a parent perſues his run-a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way child, and metes with uſury his ſubmiſſive return: So I hope (my God) as thy love was abundant in my flight,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:170576:27"/> my reclaiming will give it encreaſe. But alas! want of force and ability la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the will I have to return; I feel the reſiſtance of a cruell power, that ſtayes me. I feel not the interruption of chains and cords; but the interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of my own will, wherewith my enemy hath forged fetters impoſſible to be knocked a ſunder. My ſhelter is farre from thee, becauſe thy Salvation is far from ſinners. I ſhall expire in this ſo wild a bondage, unleſſe thy heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſupplies ſally forth, and my God have an eye over me; I am plunged in the mire and have no ſtrength to reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver my ſelfe; a Harricane of temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons doth no leſſe wrack my ſoul then the foaming waves of an enraged ſea buffets a miſerable Bottome. All hope of diſingagement from theſe encom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſing dangers fades, if the hopes of thy protection bloſſomes not. Alas! the more I eſſay to preſerve my ſelf from Shipwrack, the more I ſtrike upon the rocks and flats. Both within and without to my ſelfe, I am my owne fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170576:28"/> foe: domeſtique enemies are every where embattailed againſt me; I throw me eyes on every ſide, and diſcover not one in whom to repoſe a truſt: a Lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quey, Fear, waites at my heeles; and whereſoever I go, not one faithfull friend anſwers the diligent ſcrutiny of my ſearch: but how ſhould I find faith? why ſhould I challenge it from men, when I have forfeited mine to God? In my miſeries and afflictions, I have appealed to every one for comfort, I have found none amongſt thoſe that filled the van in my affliction, that would lend me any conſolation. I have never been happy in a true friend, ſuch have been numerous that were nothing but aire, and ſmoaked forth volleys of vaine promiſes; they have been rather dumb (my God), becauſe they vented nothing concerning thee, and becauſe their words were ſo many ſins. I have met with men void of charity, who ſwelled my faults with aggravations that I might burſt into diſpaire, who outragiouſly loaded me with detracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:170576:28"/> and endeavoured that my ſoul might ſink under their malice as well as my reputation; the impious ſwam in my favours: and declining the right paths, I have been a proſelyte to their prophaneneſſe. I am by little and little arrived to that pitch of irregularity, that although through the interpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thy grace, I have not bid farewell to religion, yet have I taxed many things in it, as frivolous and worthy of diſdaine. In fine, my God I cannot bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row an excuſe from any Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I have known thee in truth, but worſhipped thee neither in truth nor in ſpirit, on the contrary I have turned truth into lies, I have obeyed the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture before the creator, I have fiſhed for delight in things deceitfull and tranſitory, inſtead of diving for it in truth eternall. But (O my God) ſince thou haſt informed my knowledg with thy true religion, ſhake off that drowſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, my iniquities hath hung upon me: ſo guard my eyes that it may reſiſt the ſleep of death, which invades my
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:170576:29"/> ſoul, enlighten my eyes draw them up towards thee, to the end that through thy light they may behold thee who art the light eternall, which is never deficient, never extinguiſhed; which comprehends whatſoever can be ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined ſweet and delectable, that they may greedily feaſt themſelves on the viſion of thee, that they may run-over with joy, that they may wiſh for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but thee, that they may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced thou alone art truely amiable. Thou art the true light that conveyes light to all that come into the world. Dart one of thy rayes, that it may diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſipate the gloomy darkneſſe is gathered about me; worke in me a diſpoſition to come under thy wholſome lawes, to the end that my ſoul, enflamed with the fire of thy love, may languiſh after none but thee, and ſeek for no plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, but what thou reaches to her O Lord. I ſay, my ſoul let me ſay, Thine, thine it is by creation, mine only by gift and donation; preſerve a creature
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:170576:29"/> thou haſt framed according to thine own image, of whom thou wert pleaſed to become both the moulder and the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dell. Let not the pretious gift where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with thou haſt endowed me, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with thou haſt honoured me with pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedence above all the workes of thy hands miſerably periſh, and become a prey to the mouth of Hell. Stigmatize me in every part, let corroding ulcers and putrefactions creep through my fleſh, let wormes and noyſome verm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in conſume me; doe but thou pardon my ſoul, and ſtretch not forth thy hand towards it armed with tempeſts; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct me into thy pathes before our He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſpheare do leave off the departing ſunn, who (being now upon his laſt complement) add force to thy call and compells me to thee: force me (ô God) with all the Artillery of violence, that I may ſurrender my ſelf to thee and not periſh. Supplant my heart of marble with a heart of fleſh, let thy ſpirit wield the ſcepter there, that thy precepts may oblige my footſteps and thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:170576:30"/> my obſervance: let not anything in me (my God) be the motive of theſe ſavours, whoſe unworthineſſe in the abuſe of ſo many mercyes hath wholly incapacitated, but thy holy and vener<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able name alone. I muſt acknowledge the tardineſſe of my arrivall at thee, and to me it is puniſhment enough it was no timelier. But, my God, I am ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied thou ſtreightens not the time and limits it to thoſe would come and find thee out; with an equall acceptancy thou receives the tardy and the early. Although ſin be an object of thy hatred, it overskips the ſinner; nor doſt thou rejoyce at his perdition. Although the delay be tedious, yet thou expects with patience. (My God) ſweet and taking is that expreſſion, wherewith thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vives the already drooping hopes of my ſoul. Although (ſay'ſt thou) thy other loves have merited my jealous indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, returne yet unto me, and I will enfold in mine armes. What a pleaſing charme is couched in that ſaying which influenceth the ſinner with an encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:170576:30"/> although the weakneſſe of his forces bring diffidence and diſpaire? If the wicked do pennance, he ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the acquittall of his tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions; he ſhall live and not die. Can it be imagined then (ſayeſt thou) that the death of a ſinner is the effect of thy will? It fills me with conſolation to hear thee parabolize how the Shepheard find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his loſt ſheep with joy, heaved it on his ſhoulders; and how the woman who had found her piece of ſilver which ſhe had loſt, prepared a congra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulatory Goſſoping for her neighbors. When I turne over thy holy Writ, an inundation of joyfull teares breaks forth; when I incounter the ſtory of the father and the prodigall ſon, ſtrike the organs of my eares with that ſound which rouzeth ſoules from their dead ſlumbers. Let it not only find a recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacle in mine eare; but enlighten me alſo with thoſe divine Rayes, which convey to mens underſtanding, the hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of their ſinns, and at the ſame time
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:170576:31"/> overpovver the darkneſſe of them, let thy voice alvvaies eccho in my heart, ſay unto my drowſie ſoul, Hovv long vvilt thou permit the lethargy of death to ſit pale upon thy temples? how long ſhall thoſe cruel bonds retain thee cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive? It is time that thou ariſe, that thou tread better paths, that thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to me who hath ranſomed thee. Returne, returne, Shunamite, returne that I may have a reſpect for thee. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, cut of all delaies, pluck off all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mora's and haſten to me, becauſe I am thy Lord, I am thy God, who calleth thee, who wipeth away ſins, and wraps in oblivion things paſt. My God, when my eares are ſolaced with this divine rhetorick, with aſſurance I will conclude and ſay, let thy hopes my ſoul war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant repoſe, becauſe thy Lord load's thee with his bounties, lay aſide all fear and goe in queſt of him, and although the wearineſs of ſo many evill journeys hang on thee, nevertheleſſe haſten thy ſteps as thou intends to accelerate thy
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:170576:31"/> content, let not the ſenſe of thy ſins diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage thee. When thou ſhalt be as ſcarlet, thou ſhalt become as white as ſnow, thy ſins ſhall be croſſed out, they ſhall vaniſh as a ſmall cloud, ſtartle not at the cenſure of Bold and Preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, ſeeing thou fals rather under the praiſe of Obedience. My ſoul, diſpatch, go to him, he comes not to call the juſt but the ſinfull. The God offended by thee, the ſame will be thy ſaving God, the God that will cauſe thee to triumph over ſins thy mortall enemies. Why trembles thou to ſet forward? It is not a ſevere judge cites thee before him but a mercifull father that bec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens, who would give thee a teſt of his kindneſſe: Go, go freely whither mercy calls, leſt one day a court of juſtice ſummon thee. In thee, I now caſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor, my Saviour and my God, to thee I will confeſſe my ſins without the leaſt baſhfull tincture of a Bluſh, becauſe the committing of them before men &amp; the rebelling againſt thee never covered
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:170576:32"/> my face with a juſt confuſion. Let the grumbling phariſee murmur, Who can pardon ſinns but God alone. This is the voice of my God, the effects of whoſe breath is never abortive. This God that calls me overflowes with gracious ſweetneſſe, his wrath dams not up the current of his mercy; My Saviour! relying on thy promiſes it ſhall not be a fained return to thee. Thou art my Anchorage, and I hope thou wilt prove my Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance in the land of the living. Proſtrate before thy majeſty, I will leave to fear, becauſe thou haſt pleaſed to call me: but leſt thy eyes ſhould nauſeate my impurities, I will buck them in my teares, they ſhall flow continually, my couch ſhall bear a watery teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of my ſorrowes; and that I may render me acceptable to thee, I will be leſſe acceptable to my ſelfe. In conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, my God, I will endeavor not to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe the graces thou haſt laviſhed on me with ſo prodigall a liberality; and ſince I feel thy motions working in me
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:170576:32"/> I will repent my ſelfe of my ſinns to the end that purified by repentance from a refined and cleanſed heart I may ſing thy praiſes, and ſay with thy prophet, Who is like to thee? How glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ſhall thy prayſes hang on the lips of a ſinner, and of him who having ſown in tears ſhall reap in Joy.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="soliloquy">
               <pb facs="tcp:170576:33"/>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:170576:33"/>
               <head>PSALM. VII.</head>
               <p>I Am mouldy with afflictions, cankred with troubles, ruſtyed with miſeries unexpreſſible: Gild me (my God) with the Beames of thy Compaſſion. The Torrents of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity riſe upon me, they have o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-flowed the confines of my Soul, like the proud ſtreames of a ſwelling current. My ſinnes, bank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up by diſſimulation, not unſluced by confeſſion, nor laved forth by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment, are grown to ſuch a height, they have uſurped over my head, they have bowed my under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding and my will to the domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of concupiſence, or rather to the ſervitude of the Divell. Alaſs! on every ſide, are mortall ſally-ports to my Soul, from the bottom of my foot to the top of my head there is nothing which is not over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpread
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:170576:34"/> with ſerping ulcers; my enemy hath tripp'd up my heels, and like a barbarous Incenſed Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant he hath ſequeſtred me of all things, but my underſtanding; to the end that the conſciouſneſſe of my evill and ruine, might hang more weight on my ſorrows. It had been an act of favour to have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted me of all the functions of my Soul; but alaſs he hath ſpoyled me of them as to good, and left me them as to evill. He hath rocked my Soul into ſo deep a ſlumber; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though its wounds fall under its diſcovery, they fall not under ſo much ſenſe as to wiſh a cure and urge a remedy. When what was neceſſary called upon mine ears, then a deafneſſe choaked them up. I locked out the revelations of thy Truth; but when a neceſſary un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>attention ſhould ſhut out things unprofitable, and the ſollies of the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:170576:34"/> World; then my eares gaped and ſucked them in, with a greedy thirſt. The taſte of things celeſtiall was unſavory, with a loathing Antipathy I nauſeated whatſoever might nouriſh vertue in my Soul, nothing ſlid more deliciouſly off my palate then Terreſtrial Guſto's. I have not made the works of my God the proſpect of contemplations, upon this Account I have ſhared more of the beaſt then of the man: on the contrary, the vanities of the earth, have dallied my Speculations with pleaſure; with a luſt unſatiable I have been enamoured to them. The old Enemy of mankind hath not onely ſurpriſed the five Ports of my ſenſes, to cut off the paſſages of Salvation; but likewiſe ſecured to himſelf all the members of my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. He hath ſo well placed his am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſcado's, it was impoſſible to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline them. When I was moſt Indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:170576:35"/> to diſappoint him, I have mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerably dropped into his clutches: my Seeing has bin criminall and my not-ſeeing; my underſtanding, and my not-underſtanding; my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe and my ſilence; my ſtanding and my ſitting, my ſleeping and my waking, my walking and my repoſing. In fine, (my God) I have perverted the uſe of my ſenſes and all my members to actions ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and deſtructive; unchaſt deſires ſcortched me up; there was neither law natural, divine, or humane that I have not been a trepaſſer againſt, I have onely obſerved the law of ſinne. Alaſs, would I could not ſay I had obſerved it, but that I would obſerve it no longer: but becauſe I am the very ſame, and feel no al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration, I perſue worſe principles and tread in paths more perilous: my will ſhakes a Scepter over me, my Soul is gangreen'd with cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:170576:35"/> and is it ſelfe the cauſe and core of its own evil. I often quarrel with my ſelfe, that it ſhould be irk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome to me to live, but not to ſinne; my underſtanding is privy to my folly, which adds the more to my confeſſion, and in my own cenſure juſtly caſts me, Thou who embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces pleaſures with ſuch a pathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick dotage, why wallows thou ſo long in the mire, wherein thy concupiſences have bogg'd thee? Why do the affaires of the world goad thee with ſuch pricking cares? Why hunt'ſt thou with ſuch a ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venous ſent after things tranſitory and periſhing? Why miſcalls thou thoſe things good thou purchaſes with ſo much paine; yea often at the price of thy ſalvation, things which with fear thou poſſeſſeſt and muſt quit with ſorrow. VVhy (my ſoul) doſt thou forget thy race and the nobility of thy extraction, why
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:170576:36"/> art thou not aſhamed, with ſo much cowardice and puſillanimity to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to the power of thy body and ſenſes, which were placed under the Legiance. Why giveſt thou en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment to the charmes of the deceitfull promiſes of the world's witch-craft? How art thou igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant that the embleme of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt good is but an exhaled meteor that radiates for a vvhile and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly vaniſheth. Bluſh, bluſh then miſerable ſinner becauſe thou haſt declined the Creator to divert to the creature; that in the end, with a judgment rectified, thou may'ſt diſcerne the deluſions that abuſe thee. Behold how thou wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes thy ſelfe in the perſuit of a falſe good, and like to the Iſſue of a metamorphoſed Arachne, who ſpins her own entrails and weaves them into ſubtle nets onely to meſh flyes in; ſo toyleſt thou with many
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:170576:36"/> labours and troubles in the ſearch of a ſmall prey, not conſiderable in any thing but in its traine of tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, wherein it will engage thee. Once more bluſh that thou haſt plowed that, whence thou couldeſt reap no profit. Deplore the time thou haſt mis-husbanded, to the end that out of the very ſhame of it, thou may'ſt at leaſt gleane ſome harveſt. Pay thy heart to God, and thou diſcharges a due debt. Verily when I ruminate theſe diſcourſes my indignation is kindled againſt my ſelfe, that I ſhould not bequeath that to heaven which I ſo freely beſtow on earth. I am offended with my ſelfe when the reproaches of my conſcience allarum my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations, when I compare the loſs of ſo great riches with the little ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of ſo ſmall gaines. The knowledge of good lead's me not to it, but the light of evill allures
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:170576:37"/> me. My enemy hath ſchool'd my will, and adapting me to his deſires, he hath rendred me almoſt as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable as himſelfe. He loads me with Irons, and committs me to the black Rod of ſinne. But, my God, ſince thou art the God of might and of power, and holds juriſdiction over my life, diſlodge not thy auxilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry bands farre from me. Draw them forth in my aide, ſhade me under the umbrella of thy wings, that my adverſaryes may not have the view of my ruine; and that my enemy, proud of my deſtruction, may not have cauſe to boaſt, he hath trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phed over me. Break the cords that ſpanſel me and hinder my pace to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thee. Knock a-ſunder the chaines of ſinne I am ſo ſtrongly fettered in, give my enemy a taſt of thy might, let me have cauſe to make thy altars ſmoak with the ſacrifices of joy, and ſing with thy
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:170576:37"/> ſaints, What expreſſion is large enough to cloathe the power of the Lord? Who is capable of the praiſes of God, who hath plucked my ſoul out of the nets and gins of death, who hath elbowed me for falling, and preſerved me out of the throat of the lyon in my miſeries. At whoſe eares ſhall my Invocations knock, if not at thine (my God,) whom our forefathers Invocations have ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitably moved? if not at thine eares (my God,) who never fruſtrated the hopes built upon thee? Take me then under thy protection and let the whole world combate me, nothing ſhall diſmay me; I will fling a ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full eye on the aſſaults and approa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of my enemies, as long as thou embraces my quarrell and ſtands by me. Sift my heart, ſift my affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and winnow out all that is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary to thee. Caſt my ſoul in a new mould, create in me a ſecond faith,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:170576:38"/> to engraft thy graces, that they come not within the poſſibility of wither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; ſo that, having bid adieu to the vanities of the world, and its deceiving pleaſures, even the ſinner himſelfe may be allowed praiſe for the purity of his deſires. My wiſhes ayming only at thee (my God), let my petitions and ſupplications find audience. Then will I ſay with aſſurance, My ſoul, ô Lord, is in tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail with no deſires but what thou father'ſt. I am convinced, we cannot pray unleſſe thou quicken our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers with wholſome inſpirations, we cannot aſcend to thee without thou lend a pulley. Draw me then (O Lord) enlighten my Theory, that it may mend my Practice, that begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning well I may end well: draw me, my God, before my old Inveterate habits ſmother my nevv reſolutions; and my perverted vvill and confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in evill, overmaſter this dayes
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:170576:38"/> deſignes for my good: Seeing I pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe what is juſt, let me not relapſe into my former Injuſtices. Capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate thee for thy grace and my ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſpred thy rayes over me, diſpell thy darkneſſe which envellopes me. Inveſt me in thoſe pretious garments which make me acceptable to thy eyes, diſmantle me of thoſe fatall robes wherein ſin hath cloathed me. In concluſion, (my God) burthen not thy remembrance with my tranſgreſſions. Work an univerſall change in me, that becoming a new man I may bring to thy ſervice a new ſoul, new fervours; and that conſtantly perſuing thee I may have reliſh in nothing but in Jeſus my Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour and my Maſter. <hi>Laus Deo.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:170576:39"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170576:39"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
